So we're looking at loops and we've been looking at the for loop with a range and a range of numbers.
And they're potentially very powerful.
We're going to see later when we get to the game that you're going to be building that this is a very
important part of programming.
We now want to have a look at how we can use for loops, and we can use them with lists as well.
So it doesn't have to just work with with numbers.
It can actually work with text.
And we've touched on this earlier, but now we want to bring in the for loop and lists together and
show you what exciting things you can do.
Okay I'm going to delete this and we are going to create a list.
So let's create a list of let's say our favorite food.
So I'm just going to call this list food.
And hopefully you all remember how to create a list food okay.
And now we can put a couple of items in here.
So let's say I like.
Let's start with an unhealthy one.
Chocolate.
And then let's be unhealthy.
In this one we can go ham burgers.
What more delicious food can I think of?
Fries.
Okay, we'll put one healthy one just to keep my dad happy.
Carrots.
Delicious.
I do like carrots, though.
And maybe let's go with a drink.
One more drink water.
Let's just go with water.
Always taste tasty.
Okay, so here's a list of food that I like and what we what we're just going to do in this example
is we just want to loop through it.
So remember before we had a list and every time we wanted to print a element in this list like chocolate,
we had to go write a print statement and we had to say the name of the list.
And then we had to have these square brackets which get the index and give it the index of the element
we want to print.
So if we wanted to print the first element chocolate We had to put in this print statement and then
say the name of the list.
With the index we want to print in these square brackets, and running it would give us chocolate and
then say, now I wanted to print hamburgers as well.
I'd have to have a whole new statement with again the same thing, print food, and then just have the
number one and then again print food number two.
So if you actually think about it already, you can think before.
In our last lecture we looked at how that number, that variable R went one up each time the loop went
around.
So maybe we could perhaps use that to print a list.
So what we're going to do again is we're going to say four and we're going to use a variable.
Now this number R can be anything.
So let me actually call it something else.
Uh let's just say my food just to show you that this thing here doesn't have to be R.
It's just a variable.
It can be anything.
It can and it can hold anything.
So for my food in.
food.
Now that might look a little bit strange, but because we don't have that range or anything like that.
But Python is actually quite clever here, so it already knows that food over here is one, two three,
four five elements long and it starts at zero, then 123, four.
So Python already knows that.
So we don't have to tell Python how big this list is.
It already knows.
So we just have to say for my variable in our list food print that element print element in the list.
So we want it to print all of it.
So.
Print.
Food.
And again you'll notice none of these have inverted commas around them because they are variables.
They are not strings.
Over here they hold a string one of these strings but they are variable.
So no inverted commas.
So for a variable in food, print that variable.
and what this list is now going to do.
Let's run it and see.
Okay.
So all it's done is the first time this list runs, my food becomes chocolate.
Then the next time the loop runs, my food becomes hamburger.
Then the next time becomes fries and so on.
So all it's doing, just like before in our for loop with numbers, it's going one up every time it
runs.
So yeah, this is just an easier way of iterating through a list instead of writing the same statement
over and over again.
So this area just used a nice word there iterating.
That's again this is a common well it's not a common.
It's an English word we use means looping around, but it's the phrase that's normally used when we
are referring to loops.
We refer to them as iterations.
Again, it will just make you seem a whole lot cleverer.
And also note that how much shorter this code is.
If we had to write this out and we had to use print, we would have to have had five print commands.
So you can see how the use of these loops is making our code a lot more efficient.
Now imagine you make this exponentially bigger.
You have 100, 1000, 50,000 elements in a list.
Obviously, it's just not possible to write code like that.
But using the loops, we can achieve all sorts of amazing things.
Okay, so I'm just going to give you one more example but not using a list.
Now we are going to use a string.
Let's say we have a string.
And what a variable holding a string.
Um let's just go with name.
And this variable is going to be storing my name as a string.
Okay, Sarah.
Okay.
So let's just store my name Sarah in a string variable.
And now I want to loop through this.
You might be like why would you want to do this?
At the moment I'm just showing you how you can loop through a string, but it does.
Obviously, it does become very helpful later on.
I'm going to write exactly what I wrote here, but now Instead of going through this list, I want to
go through my name.
And again, this could be ah, well, let's just call it ah.
It's shorter for ah in name.
And again print that variable print.
Ah okay.
So let's actually well let's comment this out for now because we don't want to see what this does.
We already know what it does.
And if you remember how to comment this is just a quick little point here.
We did talk about comments earlier.
Um, but this is a great little trick.
Sometimes when you want a piece of code to not be executed for whatever reason, like we're showing
you here, just put the comment, some of the hashtag in front of things, and all of a sudden, uh,
Python will ignore that code.
So it's a great way to also, when you're trying to debug code, you're not sure where the problem is.
You start to cut down what's actually being run.
So you can just focus on where you think the problem is.
And so you just use comments and you can easily obviously remove them.
And then the code will be activated again.
Yeah.
So this definitely is a good way of just focusing on what you want to be focused on.
Okay.
So what are loops done here.
Basically exactly the same as what happened in the list.
What it's done is the first time the loop ran, the R became the S.
The next time it ran, it moved to being the A.
And every time it moved one up, one up, one up until we got to the end of the name and the loop stops.
So it's printed, Sara, with each letter on a new line.
Because.
Because each letter is a new letter in our string.
Well, and each letter becomes the variable r.
So that's just basically on how to loop through a string.
The first one we showed over here was how to loop through a list.
And the one in our previous example was how to loop with numbers.
So for now, this is all you need to know.
We will get into more complicated examples, but in our next lecture we are going to be looking at a
different type of loop called a while loop.